A Finding Aid to the Kenneth Snelson Papers, 1947-2016, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Kenneth Snelson papers
1947-2016
Archives of American Art
Snelson, Kenneth, 1927-2016
AAA.snelkenn
Archival Resource Key
21.8 Linear feet
The papers of artist Kenneth Snelson measure 21.8 linear feet and date from 1947-2016. While primarily known for his sculptures incorporating the structural principle of tensegrity, Snelson was also a prolific photographer and forerunner of computer art. The collection document's the artist's life and work through chronological files, correspondence, project files, gallery and exhibition files, photographic material, and printed material. Chronological files detail seven decades of personal and professional activities, beginning with Snelson's summers at Black Mountain College where he studied with Buckminster Fuller. Project files comprise nearly half of the collection and extensively document his sculptures, towers, atom model, computer art, patents, and cataloging and publishing projects.
Biographical / Historical
Kenneth Snelson (1927-2016) was a New York City based artist best known for his sculptures incorporating the structural principle of tensegrity, or tensional integrity.
Born in Pendleton, Oregon, Snelson enrolled in college in his home state, studying painting, sculpture, and engineering. In the summers of 1948 and 1949, he attended Black Mountain College and studied with Buckminster Fuller and Joseph Albers. Snelson then attended the Chicago Institute of Design from 1949-1950, and moved to New York City in 1952.
For the next decade, Snelson worked as a cameraman for documentary films, often travelling internationally. In the early 1960s, Snelson began exhibiting his sculptures, and gained representation by Dwan Gallery. Snelson completed several commissions and installations of his sculptures over the next decade, including Tower of Light, a contribution to the 1964 World's Fair, and Needle Tower, first erected in New York's Bryant Park in 1968. While continuing to work in sculpture throughout his career, Snelson began experimenting with panoramic and stereoscopic photography in the 1970s, and became a forerunner of computer art in the 1980s, using the Silicon Graphics computer to create digital sculptures.
In addition to Dwan Gallery, Snelson has shown with Sonnabend Gallery, Zabriskie Gallery, Marlborough Gallery, and the artist-run ConStruct Gallery.
Snelson has been the recipient of numerous awards and prizes including an Honorary Doctorate from the Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, awards from the American Academy of Arts and Letters, and a prize for sculpture from the National Academy of Design.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated to the Archives of American Art in 2017 by Katherine Snelson, Kenneth Snelson's widow.
Scope and Contents
The papers of artist Kenneth Snelson measure 21.8 linear feet and date from 1947-2016. While primarily known for his sculptures incorporating the structural principle of tensegrity, Snelson was also a prolific photographer and forerunner of computer art. The collection document's the artist's life and work through chronological files, correspondence, project files, gallery and exhibition files, photographic material, and printed material.
Chronological files detail seven decades of personal and professional activities, beginning with Snelson's summers at Black Mountain College where he studied with Buckminster Fuller. Files contain a diverse array of material including personal photographs, photographs of artwork, printed material, correspondence, life documents, resumes, exhibition records, drawings and sketches, supply receipts, and professional files.
Correspondence in Series 2 is primarily with artists and friends. Notable correspondents include artists Buckminster Fuller, Anthony Hill, Todd Siler, and Shinkichi Tajiri.
Project files comprise nearly half of the collection and extensively document Snelson's sculptures, towers, atom model, computer art, patents, and cataloging and publishing projects. Files include a great deal of photographic material of artwork, models, and installations, as well as sketches, notes regarding specifications, material samples, supply receipts, invoices, and correspondence with dealers, contractors, institutions, and companies commissioning work.
Exhibition and gallery files document dozens of exhibitions and galleries that have represented Snelson over the years in the Unites States, Europe, and Japan. Items include correspondence, photographic material of artworks, installations, and openings, exhibitions lists, floorplans, shipping receipts, invoices, contracts, and printed material including exhibitions catalogs, announcements, and clippings.
Photographic material includes photographic prints, slides, negatives, contact sheets, and transparencies, as well as notes that Snelson kept about camera types and photographic processes. Although personal photographs are included here, the bulk of the material pertains to Snelson's fine art photography in which he experiments with panoramic photography and stereoscopic photography.
Printed material is predominantly comprised of exhibition catalogs, although a few articles and clippings are filed here as well.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as six series.
Series 1: Chronological Files, 1948-2015 (Boxes 1-6; 5.1 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1948-2009 (Box 6; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 3: Project Files, 1947-2016 (Boxes 6-17; 10.8 linear feet)
Series 4: Exhibition and Gallery Files, 1963-2016 (Boxes 17-20; 1.5 linear feet)
Series 5: Photographic Material, 1951-2004 (Boxes 20-22; 1.8 linear feet)
Series 6: Printed Material, 1960-2015 (Boxes 22-23; 0.7 linear feet)
Sculptors -- New York (State) -- New York; Black Mountain College (Black Mountain, N.C.); Fuller, R. Buckminster (Richard Buckminster), 1895-; Tajiri, Shinkichi, 1923-2009
- Chronological Files, 1948-2015; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 5.1 Linear feet Boxes 1-6
  Scope and Contents
  Chronological files date from 1948-2015 and extensively document personal and professional activities over a seven decade period. Folders contain a great deal of personal photographs, photographs of artwork, printed material, and correspondence with friends, dealers, and curators. Other items found amongst the files include life documents, resumes, exhibition records, drawings and sketches, supply receipts, and professional files. Files from the late 1960s and early 1970s include many documents pertaining to Snelson's representation at Dwan Gallery. Files from the early 1970s and late 1980s include many letters and postcards from artist Carl Andre. Found throughout are frequent letters to his family while traveling, describing his daily activities, work, and challenges. Some folders contain copy prints and inventory lists created at a later date. Additional description of folder contents can be found at the file level. Correspondence is also found in Series 2.
  - Chronological Files, 1948-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Includes material relating to Black Mountain College
  - Chronological Files, 1948-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Includes photographic material of early artworks and Pendleton, Oregon
  - Chronological Files, 1949-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Includes photographic material of early artworks and Chicago Institute of Design
  - Chronological Files, 1951-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Includes photographic material from a 1951 trip to Europe
  - Chronological Files, 1951-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Includes documents pertaining to Snelson's work as a cameraman and trip to Hong Kong
  - Chronological Files, 1955-1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Chronological Files, 1959-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Includes photographs from a Buckminster Fuller exhibition at the Museum of Modern Art in 1959
  - Chronological Files, 1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Includes documents pertaining to Tower of Light sculpture at the World's Fair
  - Chronological Files, 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Includes photographs of Snelson's home in Sagaponack, New York
  - Chronological Files, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Chronological Files, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
    Includes a review of Snelson's work by Gregory Battcock for Arts Magazine
  - Chronological Files, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
  - Chronological Files, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Includes material relating to Needle Tower construction in Bryant Park, New York
  - Chronological Files, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Chronological Files, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Chronological Files, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Includes blueprints for studio spaces
  - Chronological Files, 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
    Includes day planners and calendars
  - Chronological Files, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Chronological Files, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Includes several letters from artist George Rickey
  - Chronological Files, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Chronological Files, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
  - Chronological Files, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
  - Chronological Files, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Chronological Files, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
  - Chronological Files, 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15-16)
  - Chronological Files, 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Chronological Files, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3-5)
  - Chronological Files, 1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Chronological Files, 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
  - Chronological Files, 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 9-10)
  - Chronological Files, 1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 11-12)
    Includes loose pages of journal entries
  - Chronological Files, 1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Chronological Files, 1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Chronological Files, 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2-3)
  - Chronological Files, 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Material pertains to Kyoto trip
  - Chronological Files, 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Material pertains to Visual Artists Rights Act testimony
  - Chronological Files, 1989-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Material pertains to the Ars Electronica festival in Linz, Austria
  - Chronological Files, 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 7-9)
  - Chronological Files, 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 10)
    Material pertains to Japan trip
  - Chronological Files, 1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 11-12)
  - Chronological Files, 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 13-14)
  - Chronological Files, 1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 15-16)
  - Chronological Files, 1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Chronological Files, 1994-2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 18)
    Material pertains to the American Academy of Arts and Letters
  - Chronological Files, 1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
    Includes "Snelson discusses Joseph Albers at Black Mountain College: a Conversation with Fred Horowitz"
  - Chronological Files, 1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Chronological Files, 1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Chronological Files, 1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Chronological Files, 1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 6-7)
    Includes material relating to a lifetime achievement award from the International Sculpture Center
  - Chronological Files, 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Chronological Files, 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Chronological Files, 2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 10-11)
  - Chronological Files, 2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 12-13)
    Includes a copy of a 1972 interview with Snelson by Mary E. Harris regarding Black Mountain College
  - Chronological Files, 2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Chronological Files, 2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 15)
    Includes material pertaining to a proposal for the World Trade Center Tower
  - Chronological Files, 2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Chronological Files, 2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Chronological Files, 2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Chronological Files, 2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Chronological Files, 2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Chronological Files, 2011-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Chronological Files, 2013-2014; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Chronological Files, 2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1948-2009; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Box 6
  The correspondence here dates from 1948-2009 and is primarily with artists and friends. Notable correspondents include artists Buckminster Fuller, Anthony Hill, Todd Siler, and Shinkichi Tajiri. Several letters from Tajiri are illustrated and include photographic material. Correspondence with Fuller also includes printed material, photographic material, and letters between Snelson and Fuller's estate. Some of the letters pertain to an ongoing intellectual property dispute that Snelson raises against Fuller. Also found here is a sequence of printed email correspondence, which Snelson organized by subject. Correspondence is also found in Series 1, 3, and 4.
  - Fuller, Buckminster, 1948-2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 4-5)
  - Hettinger, Esther and Mary Mattley, 1975-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 6)
    Snelson's art teachers from Pendleton, Oregon
  - Hill, Anthony (ARS, Arts Research Syndicate), 1974-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Siler, Todd, 1991-1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Tajiri, Shinkichi, 1976-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 9-10)
  - Emails by Subject, Archival Resource Key (Box 6)
    - Engineering, 1996-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Fan Letters, 1996-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Osteopathy, 1996-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Portrait of an Atom, 1996-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Requests for Book Information, 1996-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Tensegrity, 1996-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Holiday Cards, 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 17)
- Project Files, 1947-2016; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 10.8 Linear feet Boxes 6-17
  Project files date from 1947-2016 and comprise nearly half of the collection at 10.8 linear feet. Projects include Snelson's sculptures, towers, columns, atom model, computer pictures, patents, and cataloging and publishing projects. Files pertaining to the sculptures, towers, and columns contain a great deal of photographic material of the artwork, models, and installation. Also found are sketches, notes regarding specifications, material samples, supply receipts, invoices, and correspondence with dealers, contractors, institutions, and companies commissioning work. When known, the artwork's creation date is expressed in parentheses, while the expanded date range reflects Snelson's reworking, ongoing research, and documentation of certain projects over a period of years.
  In Snelson's atom model project, he explores parallels between the atom and one of his work processes in which simple forms are combined to create more complex forms. His research led him to communicate with scientists and write several essays expanding on the idea of his atom model. Items found here include correspondence, writings, research, notes, printed material, and photographic material depicting his atom model. Snelson worked with this model for several decades.
  Computer pictures document the artworks that Snelson created in the 1980s and 1990s using the Silicon Graphics 3130 computer and Wavefront software. Files contain correspondence, notes, and printed material pertaining to the computer and software program, as well as photographs and transparencies of dozens of artworks generated with the software.
  Patents include drawings, correspondence, notes, writings, and documents related to the patent process for several inventions, including the atom model and the concept of tensegrity. Cataloging and publishing projects seek to document life events and bodies of work. Items include writings, correspondence with publishers, a chronology, and an inventory that incorporates thumbnail images.
  Snelson's photography and panoramas can be found in Series 5.
  Arrangement
  The series is arranged as six subseries.
  3.1: Sculptures, 1948-2016
  3.2: Towers and Columns, 1960-2016
  3.3: Atom Model, 1960-2014
  3.4: Computer Pictures, 1987-1996
  3.5: Patents, 1947-2004
  3.6: Cataloging and Publishing, 1986-2015
  - Sculptures, 1948-2016; 3.1; Archival Resource Key; 7.9 Linear feet Boxes 6-14
    - Able Baker (1975), 1975-2013; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Able Charlie (1978), 1978-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Airplane Models (1992), Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Andrea's Day (1974), 2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Articulate Lip Tower, Black Tower (1960), 1960-1967; 2013; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Atom Sculptures, 1960s; 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 23-24)
    - Audrey I and II (1966), 1966-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Avenue K (1968), 1968-1969; 1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Bead Chain Pieces, 1959-2011; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Bee Tree (1981), Archival Resource Key (Box 7)
      - Correspondence, 1981-2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - Invoices, 1981-2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - Materials, 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - Notes and Specifications, 1979-2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - Photographic Material, 1981-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - Printed Material, 1979-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Cable Woven Pieces, 1973-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Cast Bronze Sculptures, 1963; 1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Cane (1984), 1984-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Cantilever (1966-1971), 1966-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Celluloid (1959), Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Celtic Pieces (1993), Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Circle and Ring Sculptures, "Study for Atomic Space", 1964; circa 2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - City Boots (1967), 1967-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - El Cordobes and El Olivo (1970), Ibiza, 2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Coronation Day (1980), Buffalo, 1978-1980; 2005-2014; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 19-20)
    - Double Shell Tetrakai (1979), 1979-2014; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Digital Stone (2007), 2011; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Dragon (1999), Archival Resource Key (Box 8)
      - Correspondence, 1997-2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
      - Full Scale Construction, 1991-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 3)
      - Invoices, 1999-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Marlborough Gallery, 2001-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - Notes and Specifications, 1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - Photographic Material, 1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 7)
      - Printed Material, 1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 8-9)
      - Salem Hub Model, 1999-2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Easter Monday (1977), 1977-2014; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Easy K I (1970), 1969-1971; 2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 12-13)
    - Easy K II (1981), Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Easy K (2001), New Zealand, Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 15-16)
    - Easy Landing (1977), 1976-1980; 2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 17-18)
    - Fair Leda (1969), Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Flat Out (1979), 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Forest Devil (1979), Archival Resource Key (Box 9)
      - Correspondence, 1977; 2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Notes and Specifications, 1970s-2000s; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 2)
      - Photographic Material, 1977-1979; 2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 3-4)
      - Printed Material, 1975-2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Forest Mouse (1975), 1975-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Four Module Piece (1968), 1968-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Four Star Poona (1988), 1988-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Four Tube Pieces, Four Chances (1979), 1979-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Free Ride Home (1974), Archival Resource Key (Box 9)
      - Correspondence, 1975-2013; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 10)
      - Notes and Specifications, 1974-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 11)
      - Photographic Material, 1974-1975; 1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 12-13)
      - Printed Material, 1974; 1982; 2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Green Guide (1975), 2014; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Greene Street I, II, and III (1975), 1975-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - IGA Hamburg Sculpture (1973), 1972-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Indexer (1979, 1999), 1999-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Hirshhorn Piece (1967), 1967-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Jewelry, 1994-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Key City (1967), 1967-1975; 2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 2-3)
    - King X (1972), 1972-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Kite Sculptures, 1971-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 5-6)
    - Ladle (1967-1970), Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Landing (1970), 1970-1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - List Piece (1967), 1967-2016; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Lorraine (1968), 1968-2011; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Makit Toy (1959), Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Mara Terry (1975), 1975-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Matrix Eight (1964), 1964-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Micro Fiche (1969-1970), Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - Mirror Mirror (1999), 1999-2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Mozart (1982), Archival Resource Key (Box 10)
      - Correspondence, 1981-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 16)
      - Invoices, 1982-1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 17)
      - Notes, 1982-1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 18)